Guide to the William Hollopeter Papers, 1869-1930 RL.11799
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Hollopeter papers
1869-1930
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hollopeter, W.C. (William Clarence), 1853-1927
RL.11799
0.75 Linear Feet
William Clarence Hollopeter was born in Muncy, Pennsylvania, and worked as a physician in Philadelphia from 1877-1917. He specialized in pediatrics and hay fever. Collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, printed materials, financial materials, and other materials relating to Hollopeter's work as a doctor.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by file title.
Biographical / Historical
William Clarence Hollopeter was born in Muncy, Pennsylvania, and worked as a physician in Philadelphia from 1877-1917. He attended the University at Lewisburg, now Bucknell University, and recieved his medical degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1877. After completing medical school, Hollopeter worked as an intern at the Presbyterian Hospital and then studied under and worked as an assistant to George Strawbridge, who was an ear, nose, and throat specialist. Hollopeter went on to work as an attending physician at the Methodist Episcopal Hospital, as Professor of Pediatrics at the Medico-Chirurgical College, as Pediatrist and Attending Physician at St. Joseph's Hospital, and as Attending Physician in Children's Diseases at the Philadelphia Hospital. Additionally, Dr. Hollopeter is the author of "Hay Fever, Its Prevention and Cure." He was married to Sara Adelaide Root (b.1858-1937), and they had four children: two sons who died in childhood (Paul and William), one son who died in 1912 from pneumonia at age 29 (Ralph), and a daughter, Sara Marguerite (b.1896).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William Hollopeter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2019.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, clippings, photographs, printed materials, financial materials, and other materials relating to Hollopeter's work as a doctor. The correspondence includes 12 letters, 7 of which relate to Hollopeter's efforts to secure positions at various Philadelphia Hospitals. Three letters appear to relate to a court case involving Hollopeter in 1877. Collection also includes a notebook with notes taken during Hollopeter's time as a student at the University at Lewisburg (Bucknell), dated 1874-1876. Includes transcriptions of two lectures delivered by Justin Rolph Loomis, the second president of the college. Topics covered in the notebook include: psychology, natural theology, and philosophy. There are also personal journal entries by Hollopeter.
Hay Fever -- 19th century; Medicine -- Practice -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Notebooks; University at Lewisburg; History of Medicine Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
- "Centennial Pithecological Magazine of the University at Lewisburg", 1875 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Satirical magazine mocking members of the 1876 graduating class of the University at Lewisburg.
- Clippings, 1876, 1912 (Box 1)
  Mostly related to the death of William Hollopeter's son, Ralph Hollopeter, in 1912.
- Clippings, 1915-1927 (Box 2)
- Financial, 1882-1927 (Box 1)
  Receipts, checks, insurance contract. There is also a notebook, dated 1925-1927, that appears to include notes from the executor of William Hollopeter's estate.
- Correspondence, 1877-1930 (Box 1)
  Letters regarding a court case in 1877 and letters regarding staff positions and board memberships at the Medico-Churigical College and St. Joseph's Hospital in Philadelphia. Includes one brief recommendation letter from prominent Philadelphia surgeon Dr. David Hayes Agnew. There is also a thank you letter regarding Hollopeter's book on hay fever.
- "Hay Fever, Its Prevention and Cure" by William Hollopeter, 1917 (Box 1)
  Inscribed by the author.
- Mortgage contract, 1894 (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1869-1918 (Box 1)
  Six photographs, mostly of William Hollopeter. Includes one hand-colored tintype.
- Photograph and short biography, 1920s (Box 2)
- Prescriptions and notes, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  Includes 5 prescriptions and notes from doctors in Philadelphia. Also includes Hollopeter prescription cover/holder. There is also a death certificate for Sarah Albright Root (likely Sara Hollopeter's mother), dated 1880.
- Registration record for medical diploma, 1890 (Box 1)
- School notebooks, 1869, 1874-1876 (Box 1)
  One small notebook, dated 1869, containing a translation of Aesop's fables from Latin. One bound notebook, dated 1874-1876, with class notes and journal entries from Hollopeter's time as a student at the University at Lewisburg (now Bucknell) and before he finished medical school at the University of Pennsylvania. Includes two lectures delivered by Justin Rolph Loomis, the second president of the University at Lewisburg. Topics/classes included: psychology, natural theology, and philosophy. There are also personal journal entries by Hollopeter.
- United States Hay Fever Association circular, 1874 (Box 1)